Guide to the Sergei Germanovich Pushkarev Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Sergei Germanovich Pushkarev papers
1925-1984
MS 1418
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
12.5
(31 boxes)
The papers include manuscripts, writings, memoirs, correspondence, and other papers documenting the literary and academic career, as well as the personal life, of Sergei G. Pushkarev.
Pushkarev, S. G. (Sergeĭ Germanovich), 1888-1980
Other Finding Aids
Additional information not yet available in the online version of the finding aid exists in the repository. Contact Manscripts and Archives for assistance.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in five series and additional material: I. Correspondence, 1946-1982. II. Manuscripts, 1950-1982. III. Printed works, 1925-1980. IV. George Verdansky files, 1946-1978. V. Personal papers, 1931-1980. Additional material.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Slavic and East European Collection, Sterling Memorial Library, 1985 and 1991.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Sergei Germanovich Pushkarev Papers consist of correspondence, manuscripts, printed material, and other papers documenting the personal life and professional career of Sergei Germanovich Pushkarev, a professor of Russian history and author. The papers date from 1925-1982 and were transferred to Manuscripts and Archives from the Slavic and East European Collections in 1985. The collection is arranged in the following five series.
The bulk of material in the Pushkarev Papers is written in the Russian language. The arrangement and description of materials follows as closely as possible to the original order of the papers as identified and received.
SERIES I, CORRESPONDENCE, 1946-1982, includes correspondence with historians and colleagues in the United States, the Soviet Union, and elsewhere. Among these individuals are: Ralph T. Fisher, Marc Ivrevich Szeftel, and Alexander I. Solzhenitsyn. Additional correspondents include editors and publishing houses, former students, public figures, personal friends and family members, and individuals associated with the Bakhmetev Archive.
SERIES II, MANUSCRIPTS, 1950-1982, contains files relating to many of Pushkarev's published and unpublished works. Handwritten and typescript drafts, research materials, and related correspondence for volumes, articles, and booklets are arranged in this series.
SERIES III, PRINTED WORKS, 1925-1980, contains photocopies and clippings of several published articles, letters, and reviews. A group of writings of other individuals, apparently collected by Pushkarev, is also arranged here.Reviews consists of published reviews of many of Pushkarev's writings.
SERIES IV, GEORGE VERNADSKY FILES, 1946-1978, includes correspondence, birthday celebration materials, obituaries, writings, and other material relating to George Vernadsky, a close friend and colleague of Pushkarev.
SERIES V. PERSONAL PAPERS, 1931-1980, consists of a variety of material including biographical information, memoirs, teaching files, and material relating to Pushkarev's experiences in displaced persons camps following World War II.
Biographical / Historical
Sergei Germanovich Pushkarev was born in Kursk Province, Russia on August 8, 1888. He attended the University of Heidelberg and the University of Leipzig, 1911-1914. Pushkarev served as a volunteer under the Provisional Government of Russia, 1917, and in the White Russian Army, 1919-1920.
Among Pushkarev's teaching positions in Russia, Czechoslovakia, and the United States was a five year term as assistant professor in Russian history at Yale University, 1950-1955. He was a member of many professional historical organizations and wrote several volumes, including Obzor russkoi istorii (A Survey of Russian History), 1953; and Rossiia v XIX veke (Nineteenth Century Russian History), 1956.
World War, 1939-1945 -- Refugees; Soviet Union -- History; Historians; Pushkarev, S. G. (Sergeĭ Germanovich), 1888-1980; Solzhenit͡syn, Aleksandr Isaevich, 1918-2008; Vernadsky, George, 1887-1973; Yale University -- Faculty
- Correspondence, 1946-1982; Series I; 3.0 linear feet (8 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains correspondence arranged in eight sections:
  Historians, United States
  Historians, USSR
  Editors
  Students
  Public figures
  Personal
  Bakhmetev Archive
  Miscellaneous, A - Z
  Each section is arranged in alphabetical order by the name of the individual(s) and/or topic. Miscellaneous and unidentified items are arranged at the end of each section.
  - Historians, United States
    - American Historical Association, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Backus, Oswald P., 1953-1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Crummey, Robert O., 1969-1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Ferguson, Alan D., 1950, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Fisher, Ralph T., Jr., [1958?]-1966, 1971-1982 (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
    - Halperin, Charles J., 1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Kucherov, Samuel, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Loewe, Karl von, 1968, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - McNeal, Robert H., 1965, 1970, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
    - Mickiewicz, Ellen Propper, 1967-1980 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
    - Moser, Charles A., 1954-1956, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Norton, Barbara T., 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Raeff, Marc, 1977-1981 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
    - Rannit, Tatiana O., 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Rannit, Aleksis and Titania, 1978-1982, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Riasanovsky, Nicholas V., 1980 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Schlacks, Charles Jr., 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Seton-Watson, Hugh, 1966-1969, [1978?] (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Szeftel, Marc Ivrevich, 1969-1982 (Box 1, Folder 24-27)
    - Treadgold, Donald W., 1981 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Uroff, Benjamin and Margaret, 1964-1965, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Miscellaneous American historians, 1950-1978 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Miscellaneous American professors, 1959-1960, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Miscellaneous American professors and their spouses, 1950-1978 (Box 2, Folder 32-33)
  - Historians, USSR
    - Andrev, Nikolai Efimovich, 1968-1978 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Andrev, N.E. and E.N., 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Arsen'ev, N.S., 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Barghoorn, F. and N., 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Bogolepov, Aleksandr Aleksandrovich, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Chavchavadze, Pavel Aleksandrovich, 1958, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Kalmykova, Aleksandra A., 1960-1963, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Karpovich, Mikhail Mikhailovich, 1949, 1953-1956 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Kiselev, Aleksandr O. (and wife), 1968-1969, [1973?]-1978 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Klimov, Aleksi Evgen'evich, 1972-1976 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Kovalevskii, P.E., 1967 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Krivoshein, Kirill Aleksandrovich, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Kurganov, Ivan Alekseevich, 1967, 1971-1972, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - fon-Lampe, _____, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Lebedev, Fëdor Tarasovich, 1949-1951, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Losskii, Nikolai Onufrievich, 1950-1958, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Maevskii, Vladislav A'binovich (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Malyshev, A.N., 1969, 1977, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 51-52)
    - Mel'gunova, Praskov'ia Evgen'eva, 1964-1974 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Odintsov, Boris Nikolaevich, 1948-1953, 1956-1957, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Oulianoff, N., 1980 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Podzianko, Tat'iana Arturovna, 1968-1971 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Popovskii, Mark, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Rudchenko, N.N., 1981 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Shcherbatov, A.P., 1979 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Shteinberg, Aaron Zakharovich, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Sol'ntsev, Konstantin Ivanovich, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - So1zhenitsyn, Aleksandr I., 1976-1981 (Box 3, Folder 62-65)
    - Sorokin, Pitirium Aleksandrovich, 1948-1958, 1967, undated (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Srechinskii, Iurii Sergeevich, 1955, 1965, 1969-1971, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Struve, Gleb, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Treml, Vladimir, 1957-1959 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Tsurikov, Aleksandr Nikolarvich, 1966-1970, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Zernv, N.M., 1963, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Miscellaneous, 1950-1981 (Box 3, Folder 72-73)
  - Editors
    - Belousov, K.G., 1966-1978 (Box 4, Folder 74-80)
    - Chekhob Publishing House, 1952, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - Clio Press, 1973-1981 (Box 4, Folder 82-83)
    - Collier, P.F. and Son, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - Encyclopaedia Britannica, 1959-1968 (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - Goul, Roman ( Novyi Zhurnal ), 1967-1976 (Box 4, Folder 86-87)
    - Holt, Rinehart and Winston, Inc, 1963-1975 (Box 4, Folder 88)
    - Mouton Publishers, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 89)
    - Posev, 1976-1978 (Box 4, Folder 90)
    - Posev: Artemov, A.N. and N.N. Rudchenko, 1979, 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 91)
    - Raeff, Marc, and. A.V. Stravrovskii, 1973-1977 (Box 4, Folder 92-93)
    - Treadgold, Donald W.( Slavic Review ), 1961-1975 (Box 5, Folder 94-96)
    - Mohrenschildt, Dimitri von ( Russian Review ), 1962-1972 (Box 5, Folder 97-98)
    - Novoye Russkoye Slovo: Goul, Roman and Andrei Sedykh, 1979-1982 (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - Yale University Press (and Yale University Library), 1955-1977 (Box 5, Folder 100)
    - Yale University Press, 1978-1982 (Box 5, Folder 101)
    - Miscellaneous, 1949-1981 (Box 5, Folder 102-110)
  - Students
    - Aronian, Sonia, 1963, 1967, undated (Box 6, Folder 111)
    - Atkin, Muriel (Mura), 1971-1972, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 112)
    - Bankoul, Masha, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 113)
    - Bem (Raiser-Bem), Tania, 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 114)
    - Boyd-Nadelhoffer, Iulia, 1954-1958, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 115)
    - Capodiluro, Luria (Svetlana), 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 116)
    - Filatova-Nepor, Lida, 1977, undated (Box 6, Folder 117)
    - Gornaia-Kumasheva, Lidiia, 1956-1958, 1962-[1970?], 1974-1978, undated (Box 6, Folder 118)
    - Grinich, Nina Petrovna (Ninochka Milovidova), 1967-1968, undated (Box 6, Folder 119)
    - Heye, Harold E., 1952-1953, undated (Box 6, Folder 120)
    - Hicks, Gillian, 1964-1965 (Box 6, Folder 121)
    - Johnston, Ada, 1963-1965, [1969?], undated (Box 6, Folder 122)
    - Kirpicheva-Bankoul, Masha, 1959-1977, undated (Box 6, Folder 123)
    - Kumasheva, Lida, 1955, 1958, 1966-1972 (Box 6, Folder 124)
    - Leavy, Stanley, 1960-1962, 1965, undated (Box 6, Folder 125)
    - Mickiewicz, Lenochka (Ellen), 1963, 1967-1968 (Box 6, Folder 126)
    - Ponomareva, Galia, 1968, 1971, undated (Box 6, Folder 127)
    - Ruditsyna, Shura, 1962-1966, 1973-1974, undated (Box 6, Folder 128-129)
    - Sanchez, Masha, 1962-1965, 1973, undated (Box 6, Folder 130)
    - Semmler, Cindy, 1970-1973, undated (Box 6, Folder 131-132)
    - Stewart, Jean, 1968-1973, undated (Box 6, Folder 133)
    - Stewart, Zhanna, 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 134)
    - Tondro, Helle, 1975-1977 (Box 6, Folder 135)
    - Vergun-Borovskaia, Lena, 1966-1978 (Box 6, Folder 136-137)
    - Woolsey, Laura, 1951, 1955, undated (Box 6, Folder 138)
    - Miscellaneous former students, 1949-1973, undated (Box 6, Folder 139-140)
    - Correspondence with former students, 1958-1982, undated (Box 6, Folder 141-142)
  - Public Figures
    - Denikina, Kseniia Vasil'evna, 1955-1968 (Box 6, Folder 143)
    - Dolgorakov, M.P., 1964, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 144)
    - Grabovskaia, Galina A., 1949-1953 (Box 6, Folder 145)
    - Kiseler, Father Aleksandr, 1969-1971 (Box 6, Folder 146)
    - NRS editors: Weinbaum, Mark Efrimovich and Adreis Sedykh, 1951-1978 (Box 6, Folder 147)
    - Panina, Sofiia Vladimirovna, 1949-1954 (Box 7, Folder 148)
    - Tolstaia, Aleksandra L'vovna, 1969-1978 (Box 7, Folder 149)
    - Zlatkovskii, Father Pavel, 1969-1970, 1976-1977 (Box 7, Folder 150)
    - Miscellaneous, 1957-1976 (Box 7, Folder 151)
  - Personal
    - Allileuva-Peters, Svetlana, undated (Box 7, Folder 152)
    - Coffin, William Sloane, Jr., 1963-1971 (Box 7, Folder 153)
    - Dolgorukov, Michail P., 1964-1965 (Box 7, Folder 154)
    - Gouncharova, Antonina Andreevna (Tëtia Tonia), 1947-1976, undated (Box 7, Folder 155)
    - Goncharova (Sadovskaia), A.A., and Ivan Goncharov, 1947, 1969-1974 (Box 7, Folder 156)
    - Kozakevich, Aleksandr Alexsandrovich, 1950, 1953-1957, 1961-1978 (Box 7, Folder 157)
    - Krausp, Marga Adovna, 1950-1958, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 158)
    - Maksimovich, Ekaterina Aleksandrovna, [1955?], 1965-1978 (Box 7, Folder 159-161)
    - Magerovskii, Lev Florianovich, 1975-1978, undated (Box 7, Folder 162-163)
    - Oreshkov, Elena Aleksnadrovna and Boris, 1962, 1966-1972, undated (Box 7, Folder 164-165)
    - Pospelovskaia, Mariana Konstantinovna, 1950-1958 (Box 7, Folder 166)
    - Shatalov, V., 1978 (Box 7, Folder 167)
    - Toll, Nina, 1973-1978 (Box 7, Folder 168)
    - Tumanskaia, Mariia Vasil'evna, 1965, 1968-1971 (Box 7, Folder 169)
    - Personal correspondence, 1978-1982 (Box 7, Folder 170)
    - Granddaughters, 1978-1980 (Box 7, Folder 171)
    - Various letters, 1978-1981 (Box 7, Folder 172)
    - Miscellaneous friends…, 1946-1978 (Box 7, Folder 173)
  - Bakhmetev Archive
    - Miscellaneous papers…, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 174)
    - S P's article in NRS …, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 175)
    - Bakhmetev Archive: Magerovskii, L.F., 1978-1982 (Box 7, Folder 176)
    - Newspaper clippings…, 1974, 1977-1981 (Box 7, Folder 177-178)
    - Correspondence with Marc Raeff, 1977-1978 (Box 7, Folder 179)
  - Miscellaneous, A - Z
    - Association of Russian-American Scholars in the U.S.A., 1978-1982 (Box 8, Folder 180)
    - Congress of Russian-Americans, Inc., 1967, 1973-1978 (Box 8, Folder 181-182)
    - Employment inquiries, 1949-1951 (Box 8, Folder 183)
    - Historical questions, 1949-1976, undated (Box 8, Folder 184-185)
    - Maksimovich, E.A. and TUZEX Foreign Trade Corp., 1967-1982 (Box 8, Folder 186)
    - New York Times, letters to the editor, 1950-1965 (Box 8, Folder 187)
    - Political activity, 1955-1975, undated (Box 8, Folder 188)
    - Proposed project: general, 1947, 1952-1960 (Box 8, Folder 189)
    - Proposed project: The Truth About Russia, 1959-1961, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 190)
    - Russian history, 1978-1982 (Box 8, Folder 191-192)
    - Taiwan, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 193)
    - U.S. election campaigns, 1964, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 194-196)
    - University Professors for Academic Order, Inc., 1970-1972, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 197)
- Manuscripts, 1950-1982; Series II; 4.0 linear feet (10 boxes)
  This series contains drafts, typescripts, and other materials relating to manuscripts arranged in eight sections:
  Source Book of Russian History to 1917
  Dictionary of Russian Historical Terms
  Obzor Russkoi Istorii
  Rossia v XIX veke
  Obshchina
  Lenin: Rossia
  Articles
  Unpublished
  - Source Book for Russian History to 1917
    - Correspondence with Yale University Press…, 1963-1973 (Box 9, Folder 198-199)
    - Bibliography, 1965, undated (Box 9, Folder 200-201)
    - Contents, 1955-1968, undated (Box 9, Folder 202)
    - Introductions, undated (Box 9, Folder 203)
    - Notes and corrections, 1957-1963, undated (Box 9, Folder 204)
    - Preface, 1965, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 205)
    - Reviews and miscellanea, [ca. 1955-1974] (Box 9, Folder 206)
    - Translators, 1950-1963 (Box 10, Folder 207)
    - G. Vernadsky's notes, 1965, undated (Box 10, Folder 208)
  - Dictionary of Russian Historical Terms
    - Correspondence with Ralph T. Fisher, Jr., 1958-1972 (Box 10, Folder 209-217)
    - Lists of terms and definitions, undated (Box 10, Folder 218)
    - Manuscript, undated (Box 11, Folder 219-220)
    - Materials, undated (Box 11, Folder 221)
    - Preparatory work, preface, 1965-1970, undated (Box 11, Folder 222-223)
    - Promotional materials…, 1970-1973 (Box 11, Folder 224)
    - Typescript: "working copy", undated (Box 12, Folder 225-227)
  - Obzor Russkoi istorii, 1953 (Box 12, Folder 228-231)
  - Rossia v XIX veke, 1956 (Box 13, Folder 232-235)
  - Obshchina …, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 236-238)
  - Lenin: Rossia, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 239-243)
  - Lenin: Rossia, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 244-245)
  - Articles
    - "About the Author", undated (Box 14, Folder 246)
    - "Drevniaia Rus,' XI-XV vv…", undated (Box 14, Folder 247)
    - "Moskovskoe gosudarstvo…", undated (Box 14, Folder 248)
    - "XVIII v", undated (Box 14, Folder 249)
    - "XIX v", undated (Box 14, Folder 250)
    - "XIX vek i nachalo XX v…", undated (Box 14, Folder 251)
    - "Krest'ianskii mir v XIX i v nachoale XX v", undated (Box 14, Folder 252)
    - "Zemskoe i gorodskoe samoupravlenie", undated (Box 14, Folder 253)
    - "Revoliutsiia 1905-1906 gg", undated (Box 14, Folder 254)
    - "Gosudarstvennaia Duma 1906-1916 gg", undated (Box 14, Folder 255)
    - "Kooperatsiia v Rossii", undated (Box 14, Folder 256)
    - "gl. XII: Svet i teui Dumskoi monarkhii (1906-1916)", undated (Box 14, Folder 257)
    - "Nachala politicheskoi svobody…", 1982 (Box 14, Folder 258)
    - "The Russian land in 'the time without government'", 1967 (Box 14, Folder 259)
    - "Don Cossacks and the Moscow government", 1968 (Box 14, Folder 260)
    - "Lenin's Foreign Policy", undated (Box 15, Folder 261)
    - "Peter the Great", 1973 (Box 15, Folder 262)
    - "Historiography of the Russian Orthodox Church", 1974 (Box 15, Folder 263)
    - "The Academy of Sciences", undated (Box 15, Folder 264)
    - "Excerpts from the Diaries of Tolstoy", undated (Box 15, Folder 265)
    - "Istoricheskii oblik russkogo krestianstva", undated (Box 15, Folder 266-268)
    - "Vvedenie: Svet i teni v russkoi istorii", undated (Box 15, Folder 269)
    - "Elementy politicheskoi svobody i…", 1976 (Box 15, Folder 270)
    - "Vnutrennii stroi i vneshnie otnosheniia…", undated (Box 15, Folder 271)
    - "Onarofnom predstavitel'stve v Rossii…", undated (Box 16, Folder 272)
    - "Byla li v Rossii 'Russifikatsiia'", undated (Box 16, Folder 273)
    - "Kratkii ocherk russk. istorii", undated (Box 16, Folder 274)
    - Posev, 1979 (Box 16, Folder 275)
    - Novoye Russkoye Slovo, 1978-1981 (Box 16, Folder 276-285)
    - Russian Review, undated (Box 16, Folder 286-288)
    - Encyclopedia Britannica, undated (Box 16, Folder 289)
    - Slavic Review, 1962-1975 (Box 16, Folder 290)
    - Russian Review, 1963-1971 (Box 16, Folder 291)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 17, Folder 292)
    - Novoye Russkoye Slovo
      - Reviews, 1961-1970 (Box 17, Folder 293)
      - Articles, 1956-1976 (Box 17, Folder 294-295)
      - Letters to the editor, 1951-1975 (Box 17, Folder 296)
    - "Historical works by S.P. Mel'gunov", undated (Box 17, Folder 297)
    - "The Wager on the Strong", undated (Box 17, Folder 298)
    - Untitled, undated (Box 17, Folder 299-300)
    - "Lectures at Fordham University", 1951-1952 (Box 17, Folder 301)
    - Notes on the History of Czechoslovakia - ROTC, 1950 (Box 17, Folder 302)
    - History of Russian and Western Saints, 1950 (Box 17, Folder 303)
    - Untitled, undated (Box 17, Folder 304)
    - Platanov, S.P. Time of Troubles, undated (Box 17, Folder 305)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 17, Folder 306)
  - Unpublished
    - Untitled, undated (Box 18, Folder 307)
    - "Muscovy without a Tsar", undated (Box 18, Folder 308)
    - "Russia and the USA" (trans.), undated (Box 18, Folder 309)
    - Untitled, undated (Box 18, Folder 310)
    - "Professor Vasilii Sergeevich Il'in", undated (Box 18, Folder 311)
    - "Untitled", undated (Box 18, Folder 312)
- Printed Works, 1925-1980; Series III; 1 linear feet (2 boxes)
  This series contains reprints and photocopies of printed works arranged in four sections:
  Letters to the editor
  Reviews
  Writings
  - Articles
    - Novoye Russkoye Slovo, 1953-1978 (Box 19, Folder 313-320)
    - Scientific: reprints, 1925-1970 (Box 19, Folder 321-326)
    - Scientific: reprints, 1970-1976 (Box 20, Folder 327-329)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 20, Folder 330-332)
  - Letters to the editor, 1950-1964 (Box 20, Folder 333)
  - Reviews
    - The Bolshevik Seizure of Power, 1973-1975 (Box 20, Folder 334)
    - Dictionary of Russian Historical Terms, 1970-1972 (Box 20, Folder 335)
    - The Emergence of Modern Russia, 1964-1965 (Box 20, Folder 336)
    - Russia in the 19th Century, 1956-1958 (Box 20, Folder 337)
    - Russian Review, 1963-1971 (Box 20, Folder 338)
    - Slavic Review, 1962-1975 (Box 20, Folder 339)
    - A Source Book for Russian History, 1973-1974 (Box 20, Folder 340)
    - Miscellaneous, 1959-1978 (Box 20, Folder 341-342)
  - Writings of Others
    - A - Z, 1948-1980 (Box 20, Folder 343-345)
- George Vernadsky Files, 1946-1978; Series IV; 0.5; (1 box)
  This series contains material arranged in alphabetical order, with two exceptions: correspondence is placed in the first four folders and miscellaneous files are placed at the end of the series.
  - Correspondence, 1946-1974 (Box 21, Folder 346-349)
  - Birthday celebrations: 70th and 80th, 1957, 1967 (Box 21, Folder 350-351)
  - Obituaries: clippings, 1973-1974 (Box 21, Folder 352)
  - Miscellaneous re: his death, 1971, 1978 (Box 21, Folder 353)
  - Writings: Sergei Pushkarev, 1972-1978 (Box 21, Folder 354-355)
  - Miscellaneous, 1954-1975, undated (Box 21, Folder 356-358)
- Personal Papers, 1931-1980; Series V; 1 lineaer feet (3 boxes)
  This series contains material arranged in alphabetical order by topic.
  - Biographical files, 1905-1981, undated (Box 22, Folder 359-361)
  - Bibliographies, notes, [ca. 1931-1979] (Box 22, Folder 362)
  - Birthdays: 80th, 85th, 90th, 1968, 1973-1974, 1978 (Box 22, Folder 363-365)
  - Budgets, 1949-1975 (Box 22, Folder 366)
  - Displaced persons
    - Camps
      - Correspondence, 1945-1949 (Box 22, Folder 267-269)
      - Documents, 1945-1949 (Box 22, Folder 370-373)
      - Miscellanea, [ca. 1945-1949] (Box 22, Folder 374)
    - Schools
      - General, 1946-1949 (Box 22, Folder 375)
      - Administration, 1946-1947 (Box 22, Folder 376)
      - Instruction, 1945-1949 (Box 23, Folder 377-378)
      - Lectures, 1947-1949 (Box 23, Folder 379)
      - Readings, [ca. 1945-1949] (Box 23, Folder 380)
      - Textbooks, 1946-1947 (Box 23, Folder 381-382)
  - Illnesses, 1956-1957, 1975-1979 (Box 23, Folder 383)
  - Lectures: public, 1949-1974 (Box 23, Folder 384)
  - Memoirs, undated (Box 24, Folder 385-390)
  - Naturalization, 1949-1954 (Box 24, Folder 391)
  - Religious association, 1951-1972 (Box 24, Folder 392)
  - Teaching files, 1948-1975 (Box 24, Folder 393-396)
  - Writings, 1971-1980, undated (Box 24, Folder 397)
  - Miscellanea, 1965-1979, undated (Box 24, Folder 398-399)
- Additional Material, 1951-1984; Accession 1991-M-074; 3 linear feet (7 boxes)
  Addition inventory by Susan Brady 1991 May
  Transferred from: the Slavic and East European Collection, Sterling Memorial Library, 1985 Apr 15
  The arrangement of the material within this addition parallels that of the original accession.
  - Correspondence
    - Historians, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Personal friends, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Rannit, Tatiana, 1975-1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Editors
      - Chekhov Publishing House, 1952-1956 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
      - Clio Press, 1971-1975 (Box 1, Folder 6-8)
      - Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 9-11)
  - Manuscripts
    - The Bolshevik Seizure of Power in 1917
      - About the author; introduction, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Bibliography, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Chronology, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Dr. Pearlstein, 1971-1972, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Index of persons, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Preparation; beginning of translation, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Preparation, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Text of first version (from Mr. Beaver), undated (Box 2, Folder 20-26)
      - Text of second version, undated (Box 3, Folder 27-32)